Inventory of the Eliot Grinnell Mears papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Eliot Grinnell Mears papers
1910-1944
25004
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (4.55 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, and photographs relating to economic conditions in the Balkans and Near East, to American commerce with Turkey, and to the American war economy during World War II.
Mears, Eliot Grinnell, 1889-1946.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1925.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Eliot Grinnell Mears was born in 1889 in Worcester, Massachusetts. He attended Harvard College, receiving his BA in 1910 and an MBA from the Harvard Graduate School of Business in 1912. From 1916 to 1920 Mears worked for the United States Bureau of Foreign and Domestic Commerce, serving as the Chief of the Foreign Service Division, the American Trade Commissioner in the Near East, and the US Trade Commissioner in Turkey. During this time, he operated primarily out of Constantinople and Athens and focused on capital flow in the defeated Ottoman Empire, particularly the Mediterranean and the Balkans. In 1921, Mears came to Stanford University as a professor of geography and international trade, working at the Stanford Graduate School of Business when it was established in 1925 and remaining in that position until his death. He also served as the director of the Hoover Library on War, Revolution, and Peace starting in 1924. Mears died from a heart attack in 1946 while on sabbatical from the University.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Eliot Grinnell Mears papers consist of correspondence, reports, and photographs relating to economic conditions in the Balkans and Near East, to American commerce with Turkey, and to the American war economy during World War II.
The papers consist chiefly of memoranda, reports, and correspondence regarding trade in the defeated Ottoman Empire during Mears’ tenure as US Trade Commissioner in Constantinople from 1919 to 1920. Some documents are in Arabic or French, particularly those that deal with Turkish production and consumption of raw material. Others address the flow of capital and resources in the Mediterranean and the Balkans. Included in the first two boxes is a collection of photographs from Mears’ years in Turkey.
Also of note is a collection of War Department training posters that were given to Mears by the US Naval Training Division. The 770 posters depict cartoon characters as naval mechanics and anti-submarine flight crews during World War II. They were designed to be displayed on ships to encourage discipline and enhance job performance.
United States. Navy Dept. Training Division.; Balkan Peninsula--Economic conditions.; Middle East--Economic conditions.; Turkey--Commerce--United States.; United States--Commerce--Turkey.; World War, 1939-1945--Economic aspects.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Notes on Turkish Black Sea ports and US-Grecian commerce, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- US Trade Commissioner reports, Constantinople, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- "Inland and Coastal Waterways and Shipping of Norway,", 1944 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Shipping manifests and imports, Turkey, 1910-1920 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Report on Turkish provinces, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Notes from a conversation with Douglas P. Miller, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Photographs documenting Mears’ years in Turkey, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Water consumption charts (in Arabic), Ottoman Rail annexes (in French), 1912-1914 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- US Trade Commissioner reports, Constantinople, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- "Report on Oil-Wells in Mesopotamia,", undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
- "Memorandum on the Bandholtz Incident,", undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
- "General Bandholtz,", 1925 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- US Trade Commissioner reports, Constantinople, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Correspondence, American Embassy in Constantinople, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 1: 14)
- "Cost and Price Equalization, Especially With Equailization Funds ('The Flexible Price Policy'),", 1942 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- "The Effectiveness of Price Control in 1941,", 1942 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- "A Study of War Finance by a Committee of the Conference on Research in Fiscal Policy (Parts One and Two),", 1942 (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
- World War II Navy training posters, undated (Boxes 3-5)